Sushovan Majhi

Postdoctoral Research Fellow, School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA smajhi[AT] berkeley.edu | Homepage | GitHub | Google Scholar | LinkedIn

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Applied Algebraic Topology, Topological Data Analysis (TDA), Computational Geometry, Pattern and Shape Matching, and Statistical Finance.

My research primarily revolves around the interface of mathematics and computer science. More specifically, I am motivated by (theoretical) problems arising in topological data analysis (TDA), applied topology, and computational geometry. I also keep a keen interest in applying tools from topology, geometry, and statistics to solve practical problems emerging in other domains, like finance and dynamical systems.

TEACHING INTERESTS

Math: General and Algebraic Topology, Differential Geometry, Differentiable Manifolds, Analysis, Linear Algebra, Calculus

Data Science: Probability Theory, Mathematical Statistics, Regression Analysis **Computer Science:** Computational Geometry, Algorithms and Data Structures

WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

January 2021-current

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

Role: The responsibilities include conducting research broadly in data science, forging new research collaborations, organizing research webinar series.

• Data Science Instructor

January 2021-current

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

Role: According to Fortune, MIDS is the No.2-ranked Master of Information and Data Science program in the US. Alongside instructing *Statistics for Data Science* for the program, I develop course materials, devise and maintain technology to facilitate learning.

• Lecturer (MIDS Program)

August 2020-December 2020

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

Role: The position offered me (off-campus) work experience during my doctoral studies, and has served as a Curricular Practical Training (CPT).

EDUCATION

• Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.

August 2014-December 2020

Advisor: Prof. Carola Wenk

Courses: computational geometry, computational topology, topological data analysis, differential geometry, differentiable manifolds, algorithms, data structures, computational complexity, applied mathematics, scientific computing.

• Master of Science in Mathematics

August 2009-May 2012

Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bangalore, India

Courses: ordinary and partial differential equations, probability theory, complex analysis, functional analysis, numerical linear algebra, measure theory, mechanics.

• Bachelor of Science in Mathematics (Hons.)

July 2006-May 2009

Ramakrishna Mission Vidyamandira, Calcutta University, West Bengal, India

Courses: calculus, real analysis, linear algebra, numerical analysis, game theory, statistics, physics.

PUBLICATIONS AND PREPRINTS

- Link Sushovan Majhi* and Carola Wenk. Distance Measures for Geometric Graphs. arXiv:2209.12869 [cs.CG], 2022
- Link Sushovan Majhi*. Vietoris–Rips Complexes of Metric Spaces Near a Metric Graph. arXiv:2204.14234 [math.AT], 2022
- Link Anish Rai, Ajit Mahata, Md Nurujjaman, Sushovan Majhi, and Kanish Debnath. A sentiment-based modeling and analysis of stock price during the COVID-19: U- and Swoosh-shaped recovery. *Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications*, 592:126810, 2022
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendarczyk, Sushovan Majhi * , and Carola Wenk. On the reconstruction of geodesic subspaces of \mathbb{R}^n . *International Journal of Computational Geometry & Applications*, 32(1):1–27, 2022
- Link Sushovan Majhi*, Jeffrey Vitter, and Carola Wenk. Approximating Gromov-Hausdorff Distance in Euclidean Space. *arXiv:1912.13008* [math.MG], 2019
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Sushovan Majhi^{*}, and Carola Wenk. Threshold-based graph reconstruction using discrete Morse theory. In *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry*, New York, NY, November 2018
- Link Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendaczyk, Sushovan Majhi * , and Carola Wenk. Topological reconstruction of metric graphs in \mathbb{R}^n . In *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry*, New York, NY, October 2017

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Topological and Statistical Methods in Predicting the Crash and Recovery of Stock Markets

March 2021-current

Collaborator: Md. Nurujjaman, NIT Sikkim, India

In the aftermath of stock market crash due to COVID-19, not all sectors recovered in the same way. We proposed novel models to capture the different types of recovery profiles for Indian stocks. We also employed the Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD) for a statistical significance analysis of our model.

We currently look into the possibility of predicting a future crash in a financial sector—using tools from Topological Data Analysis (TDA).

• Topological and Geometric Signature-Based Shape Comparison

October 2021-current

Collaborators: Erin Chambers, Liz Munch, and Carola Wenk

We consider geometric and topological signatures to concisely represent large datasets to facilitate their easy description and efficient comparison. To this end, we look for signatures in the class of algebraic, geometric, and graphical signatures. We have proposed new similarity measures for geometric graphs, and studied their computational aspects.

• Computation of Gromov-Hausdorff Distance in Euclidean Space

April 2019-December 2020

Collaborators: Helmut Alt, Jeffrey Vitter, and Carola Wenk

We investigate the computational aspects of Gromov-Hausdorff distance between sets equipped with the Euclidean metric. We used the Hausdorff distance under isometry to develop an approximation algorithm for Gromov-Hausdorff distance on the real line with a tight approximation factor of $(1 + \frac{1}{4})$.

• Topological Reconstruction of Geodesic Spaces

December 2016-May 2019

Collaborators: Brittany Fasy and Rafal Komendarczyk

Role: Research Assistant

PI: Carola Wenk (NSF CCF-161846)

We investigate the reconstruction of geodesic subspaces of Euclidean spaces using the Vietoris-Rips and Čech complexes from a dense sample around it. We propose two new sampling parameters: **distortion** of embedding and **convexity radius** of the underlying geodesic space. We guarantee a successful computation of the

^{*}First author

Betti numbers. For the special case of a planar metric graphs, we also develop an algorithm for its geometric reconstruction.

Dynamics and Prognosis of Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia (CML)

August 2012–November 2013

National Center for Biological Sciences, TIFR, Bangalore, India

Role: Junior Research Fellow

PI: Seema Nanda

In this joint effort to develop better prognostic tools for doctors, computational scientists teamed up with medical officers and biologists to understand the dynamics of CML by modeling the disease by systems of **differential equations**. In our parameter fitting, we made use of the big existing data collected from a large pool of CML patients. We also performed (statistical) **sensitivity analysis** to better understand the parameter spaces for our model.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

· Statistics for Data Science, MIDS

August 2020-current

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

The course covers the following topics: probability theory, sampling distributions, estimators and convergence theorems, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and regression.

• Undergraduate Statistics for Business Students

Summer 2019

Tulane University, USA

The course covered the following topics: sampling methods, probability theory, random variables, sampling distribution, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and linear regression.

• Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

January 2013-June 2013

Christ University and Scimetric Pvt Ltd, Bangalore, India

• Analysis, Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

November 2011-July 2012

GATE-IIT Coaching Institute, JP Nagar, Bangalore, India Graduate level, for competitive national exams, e.g., National Eligibility Test

• Analysis and Linear Algebra

February 2012-July 2012

MES College, Department of Mathematics, Malleswaram, Bangalore, India

ACADEMIC SERVICES

- I have been a reviewer for the Journal of Combinatorial Optimization.
- I have been a reviewer for conferences, like International Symposium on Computational Geometry, International Symposium on Spatial and Temporal Databases, European Workshop on Computational Geometry, ACM International Conference on Advances in Geographic Information Systems, WADS Algorithms and Data Structures Symposium.
- I organized SIAM Graduate Student Chapters at Tulane University.
- I have been organizing data science webinar series at the University of California, Berkeley.

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

Java, C, R, Python, Ruby, JavaScript, SQL, Bash.

SOFTWARE PROJECTS

Simplicial Complexes in JS

GitHub

JavaScript implementation of some of the widely used computations on simplicial complexes. The library also implements the Smith Normal Form in order to compute the homology groups of an abstract complex.

• Shape Reconstruction Visualization

WebApp | GitHub

To complement my PhD research, I implemented my topological reconstruction algorithm for planar metric graphs in this library. The library is written in JavaScript and made available to users as a web-app. *Skills*: JavaScript, HTML, CSS.

ENTREPRENEURIAL EXPERIENCE

• Scimetric Edulabs Private Limited

December 2012-April 2017

Bangalore, India

Role: co-founder and director

In this start-up venture, our objective was to motivate and train students in higher education. We won franchise to work with several private colleges in India. We coached science students for standardized entrance tests for PhD and academic jobs. The company employed 6 trainers.

SCHOLARSHIPS AND CERTIFICATES

- UGC-CSIR NET Research Fellowship, India June 2012
- TIFR Junior Research Fellowship for pursuing Integrated PhD studies at TIFR-CAM, Bangalore, India. August 2009.
- Secured grade "A" in SCIENCE TALENT SEARCH EXAMINATION
 conducted by JATIYA VIJNAN PARISAD and INDIAN SCIENCE CONGRESS ASSOCIATION

INVITED TALKS AND ACCEPTED ABSTRACTS

The 30th Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry North Carolina State University, USA

October 14-15, 2022

• **Title:** Topological Methods in the Reconstruction and Comparison of Shapes Mathematics Department, ICFAI University, Tripura, India

February, 2022

• **Title:** A Taste of Topological Data Analysis (TDA): Reconstruction of Shapes Department of Mathematics, Hunter College, NY, USA

September, 2021

• Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry Queens College, New York, USA

October, 2018

• Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry SUNY (Stony Brook), New York, USA

November, 2017

Новву

In my spare time, I write tutorials on *random* topics in order to make mathematics and statistics a little more interactive; they can be found here: https://www.smajhi.com/tutorials. I also enjoy playing the piano and classical guitar.

Last updated: October 10, 2022